{
  "reference_number": "5461",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": "Climate change is one of the biggest challenges facing people in poverty, here in New Zealand, in the Pacific and across the\n developing world. It is a global problem so New Zealand must match its bold domestic emission reduction agenda by an ambitious\n climate change strategy abroad."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "We need to take responsibility for our global emissions and the climate impacts that we have contributed to. We must achieve Net\n\n zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I want the requirement under the Paris agreement that New Zealand communicate its international contributions to climate finance to\n be included in the Zero Carbon Bill. This would involve providing the balance between funding for mitigation and adaptation projects;\n\n whether the public climate finance would be new money or money in addition to current aid to the Pacific; who would be the\n recipients of climate finance; what would be the mechanisms of the funds. Therefore domestic and global emissions must both be\n\n addressed in the best ways available to us."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Definitely not this would be an unnecessary loophole. These must be avoided at all costs."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "This is the transparency that would ensure successive governments are accountable, and would promote public engagement."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "No - emissions budgets should not be able to be changed",
      "answer_index": 9,
      "notes": "Determination to meet set targets, requires consistency."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The Zero Carbon Bill must require annual reports about New Zealand international climate change contributions to ensure our Pacific\nneighbours know what they would receive to be able to plan for adaptation to their changing environment. Regional Councils would\n\nalso need annual reports on regional finance to plan for adaptation to their changing environments. The annual reports need to be\nbuilt into the emission budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "The only consideration for setting budgets is to make sure iwi, hapu, Regional councils, and Pacific neighbours have climate finance\nto meet net zero emissions by 2050 and to plan for adaptation to their changing environment."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Only concrete plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emission budgets would build confidence for the electorate."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Access to climate finance is a matter of climate justice for, Iwi, Hapu, Regional Councils and our Pacific neighbours, therefore they all\nneed consideration in setting plans to meet budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Climate Change Commission should advise the Government and monitor their progress towards net zero emissions by 2050 but\n\nthe Government should be answerable to the Commission if they deviate from the advised pathway."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "I would like to see them ban NZ ETS, it only pretends to cut emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I would like to see equal numbers of each gender, the majority of whom are Climate Change Science Experts. Two Economists one of\neach gender, to advise on emission budgets. Four Experts in Emission Free Technologies, two of each gender. The chairperson must\n\nbe a Climate Change Science Expert. Other experts could be added once my original cohort has been met."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Adaptation must be included in the emission budgets so Net Zero Emissions are achievable by 2050 without unforeseen hiccups."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I think that organisations and individuals could report to iwi, hapu, and Regional Councils on climate change risks, and they would be\nreported back to the Enviroment Ministry for action."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "As a member of Oxfam NZ and a grandmother of four small granddaughters I think it is very important that future generations grow up\nknowing we cared about limiting emissions to NetZero by 2050, and cared about our Pacific and global neighbours."
    }
  ]
}
